Guide to the John Hall Paxton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Hall Paxton papers
1920-1961
MS 629
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
(22 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, writings, photographs and printed materials of John Hall Paxton, American foreign service officer. The papers reflect primarily Paxton's service in China from 1925 to 1949, broken only by a year in Teheran in 1943. He made a dramatic escape from China (1949) and returned to the United States. He broadcast for the Voice of America, and returned as Consul to Isfahan, Iran in 1951, where he died in 1953.His papers include reports on Chinese economic and political conditions, memoranda on Nanking and the Nationalist takeover in 1927; an account of the U.S.S. Panay incident in 1937, to which he was an eyewitness; a record of his internment in Nanking by the Japanese in 1942, and articles and letters on his escape from China in 1949. An unpublished manuscript, Consul to Sinkiang, is among the papers, as are extensive collections of photographs of China and Iran. Correspondents include Everett Drumright, Margaret Mackiernan, wife of Douglass Mackiernan, and Willys Peck.
Paxton, John Hall, 1899-1952
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Vincoe Paxton, 1972.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. 1925-1929. II. 1930-1943. III. 1944-1952. IV. Personal.
Scope and Contents
The Paxton Papers focus on John Hall Paxton's diplomatic career, 1925 to 1952. Except for several folders of Yale College manuscripts and essays from the years 1920 to 1922, the Papers contain no item dated before 1925.
The Paxton Papers are divided into four series. The first three series group materials around the three major phases of Paxton's diplomatic career. The fourth encompasses all personal material, miscellaneous material, and the papers of Paxton's second wife, Vincoe.
I. 1925 to 1929 (primarily from 1927 to 1929): The Nanking Incident and its Aftermath
The documents on this period focus on the Nationalist take-over of the American Consulate and Paxton's efforts to recover American property. These include thirty-three official reports, eleven memoranda, and several rough drafts or fragments of memoranda. Most are political or military analyses of the Nationalist regime after the Nanking Incident. Paxton's general correspondence (approximately 95 incoming and 60 outgoing) also focuses on the 1927-1929 period.
Although Paxton saved little family correspondence during this period, he did keep three letters (1927-1928) that reveal his deep dissatisfaction with the State Department's reaction to the Nanking Incident. He also saved approximately fifteen newspaper accounts of the crisis.
II. 1930 to 1943: Sino-Japanese War and American-Japanese Relations in China
Although this series concentrates on the years 1937 through 1942, it does contain some pre-1937 material. There are twenty-five memoranda on routine consulate procedures and financial records of the Nanking Consulate up to 1938. The series also contains five reports and memoranda on China's economy (1933-1934) as well as a letter from J.W. Ballantine on the banking crisis in Canton (1934). Paxton's correspondence includes a 1935 letter to Ambassador Nelson Johnson on "Sino-Japanese Relations in the Chefoo Consular District." But for the most part, few of the 560 (210 outgoing, 350 incoming) pieces of correspondence in this series concern the 1930-1936 period.
In contrast, most of the correspondence in this series and all of the thirty-four newspaper clippings deal with the Panay Incident and the internment of Americans at Nanking. There are also sixteen memoranda on the two events as well as Paxton's published account of internment in the Yale Alumni Magazine (October, 1942). Paxton's Papers also contain an anonymous diary of an American who shared Paxton's confinement. It now appears that the author was a secretary named Hilda Anderson.
Few papers survive from Paxton's brief stay in Tehran; most are letters (approximately 125) written to and from his mother about family matters. There is also one letter from his first wife, Ann, and another from his second wife, Vincoe.
III. 1944 to 1952: American Relations in Post-War China and Iran
For the years 1944 through 1946 there are seven memoranda and approximately eighty pieces of correspondence (35 outgoing, 45 incoming). Much of this material concerns U.S. foreign policy in chaotic post-war China. Three letters between Paxton and Everett Drumright (1946) and two letters between Paxton and Willys Peck (1946) reflect Paxton's disagreements with the State Department.
However, most of the material in this third series focuses on Paxton's tenure as Consul to Sinkiang and his dramatic escape from China. Memoranda from this period contain little information; most are evaluations of personnel in the Consulate. But Paxton did write an unpublished book entitled Consul to Sinkiang, and he did file a lengthy report on his escape. The Saturday Evening Post published Paxton's story of his trip out of China in an article entitled "I Escaped Over the Roof of the World" and U.S. Camera published a photo-essay of the journey. Paxton also recorded his adventures in fourteen personal letters to family and friends (1949).
Over two-thirds of the 1000 (380 outgoing, 620 incoming) pieces of correspondence in this series is dated after 1949. And much of it concerns the problems of refugees from Communist China—particularly the problems of refugees from the East Turkestan area. Paxton's correspondence also contains fourteen letters to and from Margaret Mackiernan, wife of American diplomat Douglass Mackiernan who died in northwestern China trying to escape to India. The Communist press accused Mackiernan and Paxton of espionage.
In addition to reports, correspondence, memoranda, and journalistic accounts of Paxton's experiences in Sinkiang, the papers include three valuable sets of photographs. The first set—mounted in a photo album entitled "Tihwa Area"—contains 427 black and white and 31 color photographs of the people and geography of Tihwa, Sinkiang. About one-half of the 458 photographs have captions. The second and third set record Paxton's trip over the Himalayas to escape advancing Communist troops. These two sets are virtually identical (93 color and 125 black and white photographs) and are mounted in near-identical photo albums. One album has captions; the other has a key to the photographs. Paxton also had sixty of the photographs blown up to 13 1/2" x 10 1/2" and mounted on cardboard.
There is little material on Paxton's work as Consul to Isfahan, Iran. An official report and a photograph album (122 black and white photographs) record Paxton's trip to Iran via Beruit. This and a smattering of newspaper clippings, notes on Iranian culture and language, and family correspondence are the only items in these papers that cover this phase of Paxton's career.
IV. Personal
This series contains personal material that rarely has any direct bearing on any one phase of Paxton's diplomatic career. There are three folders of Paxton's essays, poetry, short stories, and plays written at Yale (1920 to 1922). Two large folders contain lists and inventories of Paxton's personal belongings at various times in his career, and three folders hold financial correspondence between Paxton and the First National Bank of Danville, Virginia (1940-1943).
Most of the 172 pieces of family correspondence (79 outgoing, 93 incoming) comes from Paxton or his mother, Una, and most of it does not concern Paxton's work. There are, however, several significant exceptions. Three letters by Paxton written after the Nanking Incident (1927-1928) and another letter written after the Panay Incident (1937) deal with Paxton's reaction to crisis. Fourteen more letters written during Paxton's escape from China (1949) are also revealing.
This series contains the writings of others which include radio scripts, articles, pamphlets, and a bibliography. There are also seven maps of various portions of the world.
The sub-series miscellaneous includes a guest book with signatures (1929-1955), Paxton's autograph book from the Brethren of Pearl River Lodge, passports, various autobiographical notes, certificates, fifty "Sound-scriber" recording discs, miscellaneous photographs, and a watercolor painting by Una Paxton.
Vincoe Paxton's writings in these papers include two items—a published article entitled "Among Men of Asia" (1954) and a plan for nursing education in Illinois (1961). The bulk of her 255 pieces of correspondence (1950-1958)-1961) deals with John Hall Paxton. Many letters to Vincoe Paxton are condolences following her husband's death, and many outgoing letters concern her efforts to publish her husband's book, Consul to Sinkiang.
Biographical / Historical
John Hall Paxton spent the first twenty-three years of his life living alternately in the United States and China. Born July 28, 1899, in Galesburg, Illinois, Paxton was the eldest son of Presbyterian missionaries to China home on leave after the Boxer Rebellion. In 1901 Paxton left with his parents for China but returned to America in 1912 to attend Pittsburgh's Brookline Public School. One year later he returned to China, entered the Shanghai American School, and graduated with a high school diploma in 1917. Paxton came back to the United States once more in 1917 to attend Phillips Academy and then Yale College. He graduated from Yale with a B.A. in 1922.
In the fall of 1922 Paxton matriculated at Magdalene College, Cambridge, but soon moved to France where he gained admission to L'Ecole libre des Sciences Politiques in 1924. Along with V.C.C. Collum, he spent his time translating Jacques de Morgan's Prehistoric Man and other French scientific works.
The young graduate student did not remain long in France, for in late 1924 he sailed for New York to take the Foreign Service examination. After passing the test in 1925, he spent several months in training and then received an assignment to Nanking, China. Although never destined to be a major policy maker, John Hall Paxton did become a skilled reporter for the State Department during the next twenty-five turbulent years of Chinese history.
From 1925 to 1929 Paxton served as Vice-Consul to Nanking, watching four Chinese governments rise and fall within two years. Nanking finally returned to a semblence of political stability in 1927 after the bloody "Nanking Incident" when Nationalists looted foreign property and took over the city. Paxton helped evacuate foreigners during the crisis and afterwards worked to restore American property and prestige.
From 1930 to 1942 Paxton held a variety of posts in China, including Language Attaché at Peiping (1929-1931), Cousul at Canton (1932-1934), Consul at Chefoo (1934-1936), Second Secretary of the Embassy at Nanking (1937), and Consul at Shanghai on assignment to Nanking (1938-1942). In each of these positions he watched Sino-Japanese tensions escalate into open warfare.
On several occasions Paxton was more than just an observer. He directed the evacuation of foreigners from the Chinese city of Sian in 1936 and then found himself caught in the cross-fire between Chinese and Japanese forces in 1937 while aboard the U.S.S. Panay. Japanese bombers accidentally sank the American gunboat, an act which only worsened an already poor American-Japanese relationship. Paxton continued to monitor events in China until the bombing of Pearl Harbor, when Japanese troops interned the entire American Consulate at Nanking. Six months later he and his co-workers were repatriated by a Japanese exchange ship.
After a brief assignment to Tehran, Iran (1943), Paxton returned to China as a Cultural Attache (1944-1946) and later became the American Consul to Sinkiang, China's northwest province (1946-1949). From his frontier post he recorded the efforts of various Communist factions—Chinese and Russian—to win military and political control of the area. And in 1949 he gained national attention by fleeing over the Himalayas to escape advancing Communist troops.
Returning to the United States, Paxton made radio broadcasts to Asia for the Voice of America until being reassigned as Consul to Isfahan, Iran, in 1951. During this time he corresponded with many refugees from China and helped with their resettlement.
Paxton died suddenly of a heart attack on June 23, 1952 at the age of 53.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Japanese -- China; Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945; Asia; China -- History -- 1912-1949; Middle East; Nanjing (Jiangsu Sheng, China); Xinjiang Uygur Zizhiqu (China); United States -- Foreign relations -- China; Photoprints; Diplomats; Anderson, Hilda; Ballantine, Joseph, 1888-1973; Drumright, Everett; Parker, Pegge; Paxton, John Hall, 1899-1952; Paxton, Una; Paxton, Vincoe; Peck, Willys Ruggles, 1882-1952; Panay (Gunboat); Yale University -- Students; Hlavacek, Pegge
- 1925 to 1929: The Nanking Incident and its Aftermath, 1925 - 1929; Series I; 10" (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes all material on Paxton's tenure as Vice-Consul to Nanking, China. Writings in this series are divided into reports, memoranda, press releases, and clippings. Each is arranged chronologically. Outgoing correspondence is arranged chronologically, while incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - WRITINGS
    - Reports
      - Trade Lists Covering Owners & Importers of Soda Fountains..., 1925 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - "Anti-Foreign Outrages at Nanking on March 24, 1927", 1927 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Political Situation in Nanking Consular District after March 24, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Status of American Interests in Nanking six months after the Outrage, 1927 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Events & Conditions in Nanking for months Sep, Oct, Nov & Dec, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Review of Economic Conditions in Nanking Consular District nine months after the March 25 Outrage, 1927 December 24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Municipal Improvements in Nanking Kuomintang Plenary Conference as a Step Towards a Solution of the Political Dilemma, 1928 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Illegal Taxes Affecting Americans in the Nanking Consular District, 1928 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Military Organization of the Nationalist Regime, 1928 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Events & Conditions in Nanking for months Jan, Feb, Mar & Apr, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Annual Report on Commerce & Industries of Nanking Consular District for 1927, 1928 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Events & Conditions in Nanking for months May & Jun, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Events & Conditions in Nanking for months Jul & Aug, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Events & Conditions in Nanking for months Sep, Oct & Nov, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Developments in the Political Situation as Manifested at & since the 5th Plenary Conference, 1928 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - New Educational System of Nationalist China, 1928 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Reorganization of the National Government, 1928 October 31 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Highway Construction in the Nanking Consular District, 1928 December 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Post Report, 1928 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Annual Report on Political Conditions in Nanking Consular District - 1928, 1928 March 21 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Memoranda
      - "The Character of the Chinese People", [pre 1929] (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Concerning the Evacuation of Kuling, Kiangai, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - The Nanking Incident, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Immunity from Local Regulations in China, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - The Housing Problem at the Nanking Consulate, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Travel Allowance for the Nanking Consulate, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Romanizations of Names of Political & Military Leaders, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Settlement of the Nanking Incident, 1927-1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Rough Notes, 1927, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Rough Drafts & Notes, 1927-1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - "The Big Swords & the Little Swords Clash" (unofficial) (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "On What Conditions Should Missionaries Return to Places that are now Evacuated?" (unofficial), undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "Nanking - Four Months After" (unofficial), 1927 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Other Writings
      - Press Release re: Nanking Incident, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Circular re: Nanking Incident; Misc., 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Newspaper Clippings re: Nanking Incident, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Miscellaneous, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Outgoing Correspondence
      - January 1927 - December 1927, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - January 1928 - March 1928 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - (April 1928 - December 1928) - July - October 1929 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Incoming Correspondence
      - A - C, 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - D - K, 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - L - Z, 1927-1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Unidentified, 1927-1928, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
- 1930 to 1943: Sino-Japanese War and American-Japanese Relations in China, 1930 - 1943; Series II; 1'3" (3 boxes)
  Series II includes all material on Paxton's work as a middle echelon diplomat concerned with Japanese influence in China. Writings in this series are divided into reports, memoranda, press releases, clippings, speech notes, a published article, and a diary. Each is arranged chronologically.
  Outgoing correspondence is arranged chronologically, while incoming correspondence is arranged by author.
  - WRITINGS
    - Reports
      - The Canton Silk Market, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Importance of Native Banks in the Kuomintang Economy, [1934] (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - General Economic, Financial & Trade Conditions in the Canton Consular District, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Political Reports for Jul - Aug, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Post Report, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - The Chinese Banking System (unofficial), 1934 July (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Memoranda
      - Valuable Chinese Contacts, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Misc. Procedural Memos, 1932,1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Journey to Loyang by Mr. Paxton in Connection with Evacuation of Foreigners from Sian, 1937 January 26 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Plan for Protection of Americans in Nanking, 1937 March 24 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Protection of Foreigners at Nanking, 1937 August 25 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Defense of the U.S. Embassy, 1927 September 3 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Personal Experiences of Paxton at the Time of the Bombing of the U.S.S. Panay, [1938] (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Visit to Sungkiang, Kiangsu, 1939 June 6 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Memo of a Conversation, 1941 February 8 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Memo of a Meeting, 1941 March 27 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Settlement of the Case of Arrest of Dollar Lumber Co. Representatives, 1941 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Record of Events, [1941/1942] (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Misc. Office Procedures, Language Instruction & Questionnaires, (1930-1932)-1942, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Office Procedures, 1932-1934 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - Rough Drafts: (Box 3, Folder 48)
        - On the Reliability of Political & Military Intelligence, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
        - Recommendations for Improving Chinese Language Classes, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - Rough Draft (Box 3, Folder 49)
        - Secret Military Preparations to Defend the U.S. Embassy, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - Rough Draft (Box 3, Folder 50)
        - Paxton's Account of the U.S.S. Panay Incident, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Rough Draft (Box 3, Folder 51)
        - Record of Events, 1941/1942 (Box 3, Folder 51)
        - Plans for Escape, [1942?] (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Other Writings
      - Press Releases: (Box 3, Folder 53)
        - Panay Incident, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 53)
        - Wang Ching-Wei Speaks on the Anniversary of Nationalist Return to Nanking, [1939?] (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - Speech Notes: (Box 3, Folder 54)
        - "The Fear of Fear", undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
        - Other unidentified speech notes (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Newspaper clippings on the Panay Incident & Japanese Internment (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - Published article; "Interned by the Japs" in the Yale Alumni Magazine, 1942 October (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - Diary, 1941/1942 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Outgoing Correspondence
      - September 1931 - December 1934 (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - January - December 1935 (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - January 1936 - August 1938 (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - November 1938 - December 1940 (Box 4, Folder 61)
      - January - August 1941 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      - September 1941 - August 1942 (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - September - October 1942 (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - November 1942 - January 1943 (Box 4, Folder 65)
      - May - December 1943 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Incoming Correspondence
      - A - Bd, (1932-1941)-1943 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - Be - Bz, 1930, 1937-1942 (Box 4, Folder 68)
      - Ca - Chd, 1931-1935, (1937-1938)1939, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - Chefoo Club, 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 70)
      - Che - Cz, 1933-1938, 1940, [illegible] (Box 4, Folder 71)
      - Da - Dd, 1938-1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - De-Em, 1937, 1939-1940, [illegible] (Box 4, Folder 73)
      - En - G, 1932-1938, 1942-1943, undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
      - H - K, 1932-1939, 1941-1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
      - L- M, 1935-1943, undated (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - N - Sn, 1931, 1935, (1937 1943), undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - Si -Sz, 1943, 1937, 1940, (1941-1942) (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - T - W, 1935, 1937-1940, (1942) (Box 4, Folder 79)
      - X - Z, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 80)
      - Unidentified, 1931, 1935, 1937-1938, 1940-1943, undated (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - FINANCIAL RECORDS
    - Financial-Records of the U.S. Consulate at Nanking, 1927-(1930-1938) (Box 5, Folder 81a)
- 1944 to 1952: American Relations in Post-War China and Iran, 1944 - 1952; Series III; 4'7" (11 boxes)
  Series III includes all material on Paxton's involvement in post-war China, first as Cultural Attaché to Shanghai, then as Consul to Tihwa, and finally as advocate and friend of refugees from Communist China. It also contains some overlapping material on Paxton's brief tenure as Consul to Isfahan.
  Writings in this series are divided into reports, memoranda, press releases, clippings, published articles, unpublished books, and language notes. Each is arranged chronologically.
  Outgoing correspondence is arranged chronologically, while incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author.
  This series also contains photographs of Northwestern China and Iran.
  - WRITINGS
    - Reports
      - Historical Notes on Background of the Turki Language, 1949 July 30 (Box 6, Folder 82)
      - Proposed Romanization for Arabic Alphabet Used in Central Asiatic Languages, 1949 August 1 (Box 6, Folder 82)
      - Travel out of Tihwa, 1950 March 1 (Box 6, Folder 83)
      - The Comparative Study of Communication Systems, 1951 March 26 (Box 6, Folder 84)
      - Surface travel from Beirut to Isfahan [Iran], 1951 October 8 (Box 6, Folder 85)
      - "Eastern Turkistan Behind the Iron Curtain" (unofficial), 1951 (Box 6, Folder 86)
      - "Continuance of Red Terrorism in Turkistan" (unofficial), 1951 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Memoranda
      - On the Burning of the Chancery on January 20, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 87)
      - A Review of the Cultural Program in China, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 87)